In the last lecture we made sure that we can actually switch between pages but our application is constantly
Son dersimizde aslnda sayfalar arasnda gei yapabildiimizden emin olduk ama uygulama srekli yeniden
reloading and we don't want that.
ykleniyor ve bunu istemiyoruz.
Now we want to make sure that we stay inside the application when clicking on links inside of it, when
imdi dardan girerken ierisindeki balantlar tklarken ve dorudan yeni eik
coming from outside of it and directly entering /new-post,
izgi iine girerken uygulamann iinde kalmamz istiyoruz.
obviously it will reload the app if we hit enter,
Akas, giri tuuna basarsak uygulamay tekrar ykleyecektir.
that's just how the internet works,
te sadece Internet nasl alr.
We send a new request to get a new page. But inside of our application when we click links, we don't need
Yeni bir sayfa almak iin yeni bir istek gnderiyoruz, ancak uygulamanzn iindeyiz ve iimize girdiimiz iin
that behavior because we're inside of it.
bu davrana ihtiya duymadmz balantlar tklyoruz.
We can basically prevent the default and make sure no requests get sent and handle that click internally
Temelde bir varsaylan nleyebiliriz ve istek gnderilmediinden emin olabiliriz ve sayfay javascript'le tekrar girmek iin
to re-render the page with javascript.
bu tklamay dahili olarak ele alabiliriz.
For that we need to change our links,
Bunun iin balantlarmz deitirmemiz gerekiyor.
right now we use normal anchor tags
u an normal apa metin kullanyoruz.
and this is not what we really use when using react router,
Ve bu, re-act router' kullanrken gerekten kullandmz ey deil.
there are we have a special component we can use, the link component. As the name suggests, link allows
Balant bileenini kullanabildiimiz zel bir bileene sahibiz, nk gestlerin adlar balantya izin
us to
veriyor.
you guessed it, create a link.
Bir balant oluturduunu tahmin ettiniz.
We use this instead of the anchor tag,
Bunu Yank veya etiket yerine kullanyoruz.
there we use link obviously
Akas balant kullanyoruz.
also as a closing tag. Link alone of course doesn't do much because we need to tell react router where
Tabii ki tek bana bir kapan etiketi balants olarak ok fazla ey yapmyoruz nk yeniden ynlendirici ynlendirmeyi
this link should lead to.
kprye ynlendirmesi gerektiini sylemeliyiz.
We do it as with the to property, the to property in its simplest form is a string, like to='/'.
En basit biimdeki iki mlk, eik izgi gibi bir dizgeyle iki mlkte olduu gibi yaplr.
Now this is essentially kind of the same as a href="/"
imdi, ref eittir eik izgi ile ayndr.
but react router will create the anchor tag and then prevent default which would be to send a new request
Ancak yeniden ynlendirici yanker etiketi oluturacak ve ardndan yeni bir istek gndermek ve bunun yerine kendisine
and instead handle that click on itself
ait olan tklama ilemek iin varsaylan engelleyecektir.
that is why we need to use link
Bu yzden Layng'i kullanmamz gerekiyor.
Now I said in its simplest form, to is a slash, to
Hayr Basit bir biimde bir eik izgi olduunu syledim.
can also be a more complex element, it can be a javascript object and hence needs to be wrapped in single
Ayrca daha karmak bir e olabilir; bu, bir javascript nesnesi olabilir ve dolaysyla dinamik ierii retmek
curly braces to output dynamic content
iin parantezleri tek bir arya sarmanz gerekir.
and then the dynamic content is a javascript object,
Ve sonra dinamik ierik bir javascript nesnesidir.
so one more pair of curly braces.
Yani bir ift kvrck parantez daha.
And there, we can now configure where we want to go to,
Ve sonra imdi nereye gitmek istediimiz konfigre edebiliriz.
we can set up a pathname property here which then again is the string where we want to go to like
bundan sonra da gndermek iin bundan sonra potansiyel bir karma etiket ekleyebiliriz.
/new-post but we can also now add a potential hash tag after that like submit
Buraya bir pathname mlk hazrlayabiliriz, burada ileti dizininde yeni bir Slash gibi gitmek istediimiz dize yine de, ancak
which I don't have
Benim elimde olmayan bir ey var.
but this would allow us to then jump to any ID submit we have in that elements, so using that feature
Ancak bu, eleri finanse ettiimiz herhangi bir fikri atlamamz salayacakt, bu nedenle size sunulan
of appending a fragment of the URL, you might be aware of that,
bir parann eklenme zelliini kullanarak ya da bunun farknda olabilirsiniz.
you can simply add hash something after the URL to jump to that point.
Yalnzca o noktaya atladnz yerden sonra karma ey ekleyebilirsiniz.
We can also set up search and search allows us to add queryParams like quick submit equals
Aramay da ayarlayabiliriz ve arama, Eitleme Uyandrma gibi, sorgu ebeveynleri eklememizi salar.
True
Doru.
Now these are all just examples,
imdi hepsi sadece rnektir.
they won't do anything in this application but this is some advanced set up we can use to configure
Bu uygulamada hibir ey yapmayacaklar, ancak bu, bu balantlar uyguladmzda bu
where we're going to when clicking this link. With these links implemented
balanty tklattmzda nereye gideceimizi yaplandrmak iin kullanabileceimiz baz gelimi ayarlar.
now, if we save the application and go back, you will see I'm on /new-post now, if I click on home
imdi uygulamay kaydedip geri dnersek, son yeni mesajmda olduumu greceksin, imdi eve tklarsam eve
I go back to home but you will see that this reload
dnsem de bu yeniden yklemeyi greceksin.
icon actually never spins the same for new posts,
Asla ayn eyi yeni yaynlar iin harcayamam.
and here you also see that queryParams and the hash tag added to the end.
Ve burada ayrca Querrey Perham'n ve hash etiketinin sonuna eklendiini gryorsunuz.
So now we're not actually reloading the page,
imdi de aslnda sayfay yeniden yklemiyoruz.
it looks exactly like before but now simply react is re-rendering parts of the page which need to
gibi grnyor ancak imdi sadece tepki vermek, sayfann hangi blmlerinin oluturulmas gerektiini gsteriyor.
be re-rendered,
Eskiden olduu
we're not loading a new page,
Yeni bir sayfa yklemiyoruz.
we're not loading that same page again.
Ayn sayfay tekrar yklemiyoruz.
Of course when loading the same page again it's still react rendering the javascript to the DOM
Tabii ki ayn sayfay tekrar yklerken yine de javascripti DOM'a dndryor.
but as I said we'll actually reload the page whilst doing that and therefore lose our state.
Ama dediim gibi, bunu yaparken sayfay yeniden ykleyeceiz ve bu nedenle durumumuzu kaybedeceiz.
Now our state is contained,
imdi devletimiz ieriliyor.
we don't reload the application
Uygulamay yeniden yklemiyoruz.
and this is the way we should actually navigate around
Ve aslnda etrafmzdan dolamamz gereken yol budur.
therefore, using the link component.
Bu nedenle de-link bileenini kullanarak.